Guide to the New American Movement Records TAM.051
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
New American Movement Records
1971-1982
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
New American Movement (Organization)
Blau, Joel
TAM.051
22.25 Linear Feet in 19 record cartons, 3 manuscript boxes, and 1 oversize flat box
The New American Movement (NAM) was established in 1972 by veterans of the New Left who wanted to move beyond the activism of the 1960s and rejected a Communist "vanguard party" approach to organizing. NAM's overarching goal was to create a democratic socialist society, characterized by racial, sexual and economic equality. In 1982, the organization joined with the Democratic Socialist Organizing Committee to form the Democratic Socialists of America. This collection contains conference and convention materials, correspondence, meeting minutes and agendas, position papers, reports, educational materials, and printed ephemera. The collection also contains some files on other socialist and left organizations, some of which contain discussion of NAM's relations with these organizations.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Materials found in repository; provenance is unknown. Accession numbers associated with this collection are 1980.009 and 2011.016. Additionally, a copy of a police report on the New American Movement was donated by Joel Blau in 1998; its associated accession number is 2014.077. One box of conference position papers and organizational literature was found in repository and added to the collection in 2018. The accession number associated with this gift is 2018.008.
One manuscript box of mixed material was found in the repositiory and added to the collection in June 2018. The accession number associated with this accretion is 2018.087. One banner was found in the repository in 2019; the accession number associated with this item is 2019.047.
Arrangement
With the exception of box 18, this collection has not been arranged by an archivist. The majority of materials are arranged in the order in which they were received from the donor.
Historical Note
The New American Movement (NAM), a self-identified "new type" of socialist organization, held its founding convention in Minneapolis, Minnesota in 1972. Established largely by veterans of the New Left, NAM wanted to move beyond the activism of the 1960s and rejected a Communist "vanguard party" approach to organizing. The group was opposed to the Vietnam War and called for the impeachment of President Richard M. Nixon. NAM's overarching goal was to create a democratic socialist society, characterized by racial, sexual and economic equality. In 1982, the organization joined with the Democratic Socialist Organizing Committee, led by Michael Harrington, to form the Democratic Socialists of America.
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Democratic Socialists of America Records (TAM 105)
Michael Harrington Papers (TAM 209)
Scope and Contents
The New American Movement Records (1971-1982) consist of correspondence, meeting minutes and agendas, conference and convention materials, position papers, reports, educational materials, and printed ephemera. The collection includes materials related to various New American Movement (NAM) committees, commissions, task forces, and regional chapter files. There are also files on other socialist and left organizations, some of which contain discussion of NAM's relations with these organizations, including discussion within NAM on whether or not to merge with the Democratic Socialist Organizing Committee to form the Democratic Socialists of America.
Material from NAM conventions includes notes, resolutions, agendas, statements, convention packets, song sheets, correspondence, planning and workshop materials.
Position paper topics address discrimination against women, racism, foreign policy, occupational health and safety, fair taxation, housing and other economic issues. The collection also contains statements addressing NAM strategies and activity proposals.
Printed ephemera found in the collection includes some issues of Discussion Bulletin, Move On, Red Gargoyle, Gateway Star and other regional newsletters. There is also a selection of materials regarding the production of some NAM publications.
The collection contains a variety of material produced by the NAM National Office, National Interim Committee, the Expanded National Interim Committee, and the Political Committee. NAM commissions, caucuses and task forces documented in the collection include the Anti-Racism Commission, Campus Commission, Class Study Commission, Economic Task Force, Electoral Commission, Energy Commission, Gay Caucus, Health Commission, Commission on Internationalism, Labor Commission, Marxist Leninist Caucus, Occupational Health and Safety Task Force, Socialist Feminists, Urban Commission, and others.
Regional chapter files include correspondence, newsletters, position papers, agendas and notes from NAM chapters across the country. Represented regions include the Industrial Heartland, Midwest, West Coast, Southwest, Rocky Mountain Region, South, Northwest, and Northeast chapters. There are materials on both active and inactive chapters, chapter evaluations, chapter report summaries and rejected NAM Chapter applications.
Correspondence with other organizations, parties, and groups includes some ephemera produced by those organizations. Organizations represented in the collection include ACORN, American Friends Service Committee, Christians for Socialism, Coalition for New Foreign and Military Policies, Freedom Socialist Party, International Socialists, Movement for Economic Justice, National Alliance Against Racism and Political Repression, National Black Political Assembly, New Action Party, New Democratic Party, People's Party, Socialist Party USA, Sojourner Truth Organization, War Resistance League, Wisconsin Alliance and others.
One box of materials added to the collection in 2018 includes additional position papers, resolutions, statements, and proposals related to the 1972 Founding Constitutional Conference, as well as organizational literature and pamphlets produced around the same time.
Correspondence.; Bulletins.; New Left -- United States.; Minutes (administrative records); Reports.; Printed ephemera.; Socialist parties -- United States.; Student movements -- United States.; Socialism and youth -- United States.; Socialist feminism.; New American Movement (Organization); Democratic Socialist Organizing Committee (U.S.); Democratic Socialists of America; Blau, Joel
- National Office correspondence, 1971-1972 (Box 1)
- Regional chapter correspondence, 1976-1979 (Box 1)
- Northeast region and general correspondence, 1976-1979; 556327 (Box 2)
- Conventions, 1976-1981 (Box 2)
- Conventions, 1972-1975; 556326 (Box 3)
- Movement organizing literature, proposals and papers, 1971-1972 (Box 3)
- Correspondence with other organizations, 1972-1979 (Box 3)
- Schools and training sessions, 1977-1979; 556325 (Box 4)
- Newspaper correspondence, editorial policy, 1973-1976 (Box 4)
- Chapter evaluations, 1980 (Box 4)
- Chapter reports and summaries, 1973-1976 (Box 4)
- Commissions and caucuses, 1972-1979 (Box 4)
- Meeting minutes, newsletters and reports, 1972-1981 (Box 4)
- National Office mailings, 1971-1981; 556324 (Box 5)
- National Interim Committee notes, 1980-1981 (Box 5)
- National Interim Committee, Political Committee, and individual correspondence, 1975-1978 (Box 5)
- Membership mailings and correspondence, statements, drafts and notes, 1980-1982; 556322 (Box 6)
- Committees, 1972-1973, 1980-1982 (Box 6)
- Printed ephemera, including NAM Women's newsletters, 1973-1981 (Box 6)
- National Interim Committee and Expanded National Interim Committee files, 1974-1981; 556321 (Box 7)
- Regional chapter files, 1971-1973; 556320 (Box 8)
- Davenport Conference, 1971; 556319 (Box 8)
- Dorothy Healey's files, 1974-1976 (Box 9)
- Movement organizing literature and mailings, 1972 (Box 9)
- Meeting notes, 1981 (Box 9)
- Travel reports, 1971-1979 (Box 9)
- Publication production files, including Moving On and Discussion Bulletin, 1976-1980 (Box 9)
- Speaker's bureau, 1976-1977 (Box 9)
- NAM constitution and by-laws, 1976 (Box 9)
- Fundraising, 1975-1979 (Box 9)
- General office files, 1976-1978 (Box 10)
- Correspondence with other organizations, 1973-1979; 556318 (Box 10)
- Correspondence with other organizations, 1973-1978; 556317 (Box 11)
- Movement organizing literature, 1972 (Box 11)
- Regional chapter files, 1973-1980 (Box 11)
- Regional chapter files, 1973-1980; 556316 (Box 12)
- Regional chapter files, 1973-1980; 556315 (Box 13)
- Regional chapter files, 1973-1980; 556314 (Box 14)
- Commissions, 1978-1981; 556313 (Box 15)
- Conventions, 1972-1974, 1977 (Box 15)
- National Office, National Interim Committee, and Expanded National Interim Committee files, 1972-1977 (Box 15)
- Commissions and task forces, 1971-1979; 556312 (Box 16)
- Printed ephemera, 1972-1982; 556311 (Box 17)
- Correspondence and ephemera gathered by NAM Queens Chapter, includes material from NAM and other organizations, 1972-1974; 556310 (Box 17)
- Police report, 1972 (Box 17)
- Conferences, 1971-1973; 556356 (Box 18)
- National Interim Committee files, 1971-1978; 556351 (Box 18)
- Regional chapter files, 1971-1973; 556348 (Box 18)
- Committees and task forces, 1972; 556349 (Box 18)
- Position papers, proposals, and press releases, 1971-1973; 556337 (Box 18)
- Socialist-Feminist Conference, 1975; 556332 (Box 18)
- Printed ephemera and statements from other organizations, 1970-1973; 556331 (Box 18)
- Printed ephemera, 2011 accession, 1975-1982; 556309 (Box 19)
- Commissions and caucuses, 1975-1981; 556308 (Box 20)
- Parliamentary procedures and constitution, 1975-1976 (Box 20)
- Regional chapter files, primarily West Coast, St. Louis and Southside Chicago, 1975-1981 (Box 20)
- Printed ephemera, primarily regional newsletters, 1975-1982 (Box 20)
- Conference Position Papers and Organizational Literature, 1971-1974 (Box 21)
- June 2018 Accretion: Position Papers, 1972-1980 (Box 22, Folder 1-2)
  Scope and Contents
  The New American Movement June 2018 Accretion contain position paper publications from 1972 to 1981. Position paper topics address discrimination against women, racism, foreign policy, occupational health and safety, fair taxation, housing and other economic issues.
  Arrangement
  This series has not been arranged by an archivist. The materials are arranged in the order in which they were received from the donor.
- Banner, undated (Box 23)